Guide to the Health and Welfare Federation of Allegheny County Records, Pittsburgh, Pa. 1943-1950 AIS.1968.14a
ULS Archives & Special Collections
Health and Welfare Federation of Allegheny County, Pittsburgh, Pa. Records
1943-1950
ULS Archives & Special Collections
Health and Welfare Association of Allegheny County
AIS.1968.14a
10.63 Linear Feet
The Health and Welfare Federation of Allegheny County organized in March, 1943, as the Federation of Social Agencies of Pittsburgh and Allegheny County. The Federation promoted cooperation among the social agencies of Pittsburgh and surrounding vicinity for the improvement of social conditions and development of an adequate welfare program for the community. The collection includes the constitution and by-laws of the organization and its divisions, organizational charts, correspondence, minutes, reports, and publications of the agency.
History
The Health and Welfare Federation of Allegheny County organized in March, 1943, as the Federation of Social Agencies of Pittsburgh and Allegheny County. The Federation promoted cooperation among the social agencies of Pittsburgh and surrounding vicinity for the improvement of social conditions and development of an adequate welfare program for the community. The Federation did so through research into social conditions and social facilities, budgetary planning on a community-wide basis, undertaking for the promotion of group thinking and joint planning, setting appropriate measures for the raising of standards in social service and the development of public understanding and support of social work. The Federation was composed of agencies which were engaged in health and/or welfare work in Allegheny County.
Scope and Content Notes
This collection contains the constitution and by-laws of the organization and its divisions, organizational charts, correspondence, minutes and reports of committees including budget reviews of the Community Fund Agencies, and publications of the agency.
Access Restrictions
No restrictions.
Acquisition Information
This collection came to the Archives Service Center from the Graduate School of Social Work, University of Pittsburgh, on August 15, 1968.
Previous Citation
Health and Welfare Federation of Allegheny County, Pittsburgh, Pa., Records 1943-1950, AIS.1968.14a, Archives Service Center, University of Pittsburgh
Health and Welfare Federation of Allegheny County, Pittsburgh, Pa. Records, 1943-1950, ais 68:14A, Archives of Industrial Society, University of Pittsburgh
County government records; Social action; Government; Allegheny County (Pa.) -- Social conditions; Public welfare -- Pennsylvania -- Allegheny County; Health and medicine; Health and Welfare Association of Allegheny County
- Organizational Information, I.
  - Constitution, by-laws of the organization and its divisions (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Organizational Chart (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - President: Mrs. Walter S. Church (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Board of Directors (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Affiliate Advisory Conference (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Executive Director (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Health Division (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Bureau of Social Research (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Volunteer Bureau (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Volunteer Bureau, The Holiday Center (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Budget Review Committee, 1943-1950; II.
  Scope and Content Notes
  Boxes 2-6 contain volumes that include the information on the Budget Review Committee. For most years, the volumes include the budget reviews of the Community Fund agencies. For some years, recommendations for allotments and the resulting reports are included. Box 4 contains a 1948 Memorandum to the Federation of Group Work. Box 6 includes a report on the Pittsburgh Housing Association from 1951 and a report of the Career in Social Work Committee.
  - 1944-1945 (Box 2)
  - 1946 (Box 3)
  - 1947-1948 (Box 4)
  - 1949 (Box 5)
  - 1951 (Box 6)
- Central Policy and Budget Committee, 1944-1950; III.
  Boxes 7-14 include minutes of the Central Policy and Budget Committee. In addition, Box 9 contains a report on the Plain Facts 19th Annual Campaign. Box 12 consists of minutes and a report on the 1949 budget and analytical tables from a meeting held in July, 1948. Box 14 contains minutes, a List of Agencies for the Family and Child Welfare Division, the 1944 Community Fund Allotments to Agencies in the Family and Child Welfare Division, and the report on the recommended allotments to the Community Fund agencies for 1945 from a meeting held in August, 1944.
  - July 1944-May 1945 (Box 7)
  - June 1945-December 1946 (Box 8)
  - December 1946-December 1947 (Box 9)
  - January 1948-June 1948 (Box 10)
  - October 1948-May 1949 (Box 11)
  - July 1948-September 1949 (Box 12)
  - December 1949-September 1950 (Box 13)
  - 1944, 1945, 1950 (Box 14)
  - Files in re 1948 budgeting process (Box 15, Folder 1-3)
  - Files in re 1949 budgeting process (Box 15, Folder 4-5)
  - Files in re 1950 budgeting process (Box 15, Folder 6)
- Other Committees, IV.
  - Committee on Personnel Practices (Box 16, Folder 1)
  - Executive Committee (Box 16, Folder 2)
  - Public Affairs Committee (Box 16, Folder 3)
  - Recreational Education Committee (Box 16, Folder 4)
  - Report of Study Committee to Joint Executive Committees of Community Chest and Federation of Social Agencies, 1949 (Box 16, Folder 5)
  - Second Report of Study Committee to Board of Directors, 1950 (Box 16, Folder 6)
- Correspondence, V.
  - American Service Institute (Box 16, Folder 7)
  - American Camping Association (Box 16, Folder 8)
  - American Camping Association, Camp Council (Box 16, Folder 9)
  - Social Service Exchange (Box 16, Folder 10)
- Plans, Programs, Reports, and Newspaper Clippings, VI.
  - Priorities Plan (for formulation priorities in Health and Welfare field) (Box 16, Folder 11)
  - Summary of Discussion to Evaluate HWA Priorities Plan, April 4, 1963 (Box 16, Folder 12)
  - Committee on Priorities Plan (Box 16, Folder 13)
  - Program (Box 16, Folder 14)
  - Staff Conference (Box 16, Folder 15)
  - Reports (Box 16, Folder 16)
  - Newspaper Clippings (Box 16, Folder 17)
- Publications, 1943-1958; VIII.
  - Report on Personnel Policies and Procedures of Social Agencies in Pittsburgh and Allegheny County, Pittsburgh, PA by the Federation of Social Agencies of Pittsburgh and Allegheny County, July 1946 (Box 17, Folder 1)
  - Personnel Policies and Procedures of Social Agencies in Pittsburgh and Allegheny County, Pittsburgh, PA by the Federation of Social Agencies of Pittsburgh and Allegheny County, November 1946 (Box 17, Folder 2)
  - Biennial Report... by the Federation of Social Agencies of Pittsburgh and Allegheny County, Bureau of Social Research, July 1943-June 1945 (Box 17, Folder 3)
  - Day Camping in Allegheny County; a Descriptive Study of Eleven Camps Operating in the Summer of 1947, Pittsburgh by the Federation of Social Agencies of Pittsburgh and Allegheny County, Bureau of Social Research, May 1949 (Box 17, Folder 4)
  - Direct Assistance and Work Programs: Allegheny County, 1941-1947 by the Federation of Social Agencies of Pittsburgh and Allegheny County, Bureau of Social Research, 1948 (Box 17, Folder 5)
  - Recreational Facilities, Pittsburgh and Allegheny County,(Map Supplement) by the Federation of Social Agencies of Pittsburgh. and Allegheny County, Bureau of Social Research, January 1947 (Box 17, Folder 6)
  - Community Statistics by the Federation of Social Agencies of Pittsburgh and Allegheny County, Bureau of Social Research, Summer, Autumn and Winter 1948 (Box 17, Folder 7)
  - Demand for Recreation in White Oak by the Health and Welfare Federation of Allegheny County, Bureau of Social Research, June 1955 (Box 17, Folder 8)
  - Yesterday and Tomorrow; the Story of Two Years Work by the Citizens of Pittsburgh and Allegheny County, Toward Better Community Services; May, 1953 - May, 1955 by the Health and Welfare Federation of Allegheny County, October 1955 (Box 17, Folder 9)
  - Annual Report by the Health and Welfare Association of Allegheny County, 1956, 1957-1958 (Box 17, Folder 10)
  - Federation Notes by the Health and Welfare Federation of Allegheny County, October 1957 (Box 17, Folder 11)
  - New Direction in Health and Welfare Planning; A Study of the Health and Welfare Federation of Allegheny County, Pittsburgh by the Pennsylvania Economy League, Inc., Western Division, 1957 (Box 17, Folder 12)
  - Memorandum on Executive Director's Appraisal of the Pennsylvania Economy League's Recommendation, Elmer J. Tropman, Executive Director, September 9, 1957 (Box 17, Folder 13)
  - A Study of Boards of Directors in Health, Welfare,and Recreation Agencies Serving Allegheny County, Pittsburgh by the Health and Welfare Federation of Allegheny County, Bureau of Social Research, May 1954 (Box 17, Folder 14)
  - Trends in Protective and Foster Care in Allegheny County, 1939-1946 by the Health and Welfare Federation of Allegheny County, Bureau of Social Research, August 1948 (Box 17, Folder 15)